Finding Aid for Institute for Social Research (University of Michigan) publications, 1946-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Institute for Social Research (University of Michigan) publications
1946-2006
1950-1990
University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.
9767 Bimu C6 2
The ISR Publications contains publications of the Institute for Social Research and several sub-units, especially the Survey Research Center. The publications include annual reports, histories, bibliographies, newsletters, brochures and research reports.
6.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (donor # 3563 )
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The publications are open for research.
For a historical sketch see the finding aid for Institute for Social Research (University of Michigan), records.
The ISR Publications include annual reports, bibliographies and book catalogs, brochures, histories, lectures, newsletters, such as FYI and Open Channel, and reports such as Perceptions of safety and security at the University of Michigan. Contains annual reports, bibliographies, brochures, bulletins and course catalogs, manuals, newsletters, and reports from the Center for Political Studies, Center for Research on Utilization of Scientific Knowledge, CIEL Project: Computers in Early Literacy, Inter-university Consortium for Political Research, National Archive of Computerized Data on Aging, Research Center for Group Dynamics, and the Survey Research Center.
The Publications series (7.5 linear feet) consists of three subseries: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, and Topical Publications.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.; University of Michigan. Center for Political Studies.; University of Michigan. Center for Research on Utilization of Scientific Knowledge.; National Archive of Computerized Data on Aging (U.S.); University of Michigan. Research Center for Group Dynamics.; University of Michigan. Survey Research Center.; University of Michigan. Computers in Early Learning Project.
Publications:
FYI.; Open channel.; Perceptions of safety and security at the University of Michigan.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Center for Political Studies.; University of Michigan. Center for Research on Utilization of Scientific Knowledge.; National Archive of Computerized Data on Aging (U.S.); University of Michigan. Research Center for Group Dynamics.; University of Michigan. Survey Research Center.; University of Michigan. Computers in Early Learning Project.
Genre Terms:
Annual reports.; Pamphlets.; Bibliographies.; Brochures.; Histories.; Lectures.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Reports.
- Publications
  - Unit Publications
    The Unit Publications subseries includes annual reports, bibliographies, brochures, histories, lectures, newsletters, and reports.
    Under annual reports the researcher will find the Annual Report to the President for the years from 1950/1951 to 1966/1967. During this time the unit reports were edited, so the annual reports found in this publications group may differ significantly from the annual report published in the President's Report. From 1967/1968 the President's Report published the unit annual reports as sent. However, the 1973/1974 Annual Report of ISR is also very different from the one found in the President's Report. The 1984/1985 Annual Report of ISR was maintained because the President's Report ceased publication in 1984. Reports that cover a span of twenty years or more have been included in the annual reports because the majority of the publications focus on the year when the publication was written. The annual reports are arranged chronologically by date of the report.
    In addition, there are several bibliographies or book catalogs which provide an extensive list of all the publications published since the founding of the Institute in 1946 until approximately 1987. These are arranged alphabetically by title of the bibliography. This subseries also includes brochures announcing the availability of various ISR publications. They are arranged alphabetically by title of publication.
    There are five histories available with the most recent published in 1966. The lectures are a compilation of papers presented by the staff of ISR at the 1949 meeting in Denver, Colorado, of the American Psychological Association.
    Several newsletter titles are included in this publications subseries. Driving Development Newsletter was produced in 1970. Open Channel issued from 1969 through 1973, was the predecessor of FYI. FYI was printed from 1975 to 1991 and served as the unit newsletter. Freestyle circulated from 1978-1980 and functioned as a newsletter for the national test sites. The ISR Newsletter was published from 1966 to 1992 and functioned as an outreach publication. In 1994 it was issued as volume 18 under the new title Profiles: The ISR Newsletter. It ceased publication in 1995. The ISR Sampler is an annual newsletter that began publication in 2000.
    There are several reports arranged alphabetically by title in this subseries. The bulk of the reports were issued from the mid-1980s to the present. Most of the reports are about the University of Michigan campus and specific departments. Of special note is the study Perceptions of Safety and Security at the University of Michigan which includes the report to the Task Force on Campus Security and Safety and also the summary report, technical report, questionnaire, codebook, and breakdown of responses by occupation, sex, and race of respondent.
    - Annual Reports
      - Undated Institute for Social Research: A Report of Recent Activities (Box 1)
      - Annual Report to the President, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
      - 1952, Institute for Social Research (Box 1)
      - 1952, Institute Report (Box 1)
      - 1952/1953-1966/1967 Annual Report to the President, 4 folders (Box 1)
      - , Institute for Social Research: A Report of Recent Activities, 1968 (Box 1)
      - , The Institute for Social Research: A Quarter Century of Social Research, 1971 (Box 1)
      - 1973/1974 Annual Report to the President (Box 1)
      - 1980 Institute for Social Research: A Report of Recent Activities (Box 1)
      - 1984/1985-1987/88 Annual President's Report (Box 1)
      - ISR 1991 (Box 1)
    - Bibliographies
      - Bibliography--Stanley E. Seashore, undated (Box 1)
      - Books from the Institute for Social Research, 1982 (Box 1)
      - Books in Print
        - 1969-1981, 5 folders (Box 1)
        - 1983-1987, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - ISR Bibliography, 1970-1990, 1992 (Box 1)
      - ISR Bibliography, 1970-1994 Author Listing, 1995 (Box 1)
      - ISR Books, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
      - ISR Bookshelf, 1979; undated (Box 1)
      - ISR List of Publications
        - 1971-1973, 1973 (Box 1)
        - 1971-1975, 1976 (Box 1)
        - 1971-1981, 1981 (Box 1)
      - Institute for Social Research Publications, 1946-1956, undated (Box 1)
      - List of Publications
        - 1946-1960, 1965 (Box 1)
        - 1961-1965, 1965 (Box 1)
        - 1966 (Box 1)
        - 1966-1967, 1968 (Box 1)
        - 1966-1968, 1969 (Box 1)
        - 1966-1969, 1970 (Box 1)
        - 1966-1970, 1971 (Box 1)
        - 1971-1975, 1976 (Box 1)
      - New Publications on Economic Behavior, June 1956-March 1958 (Box 2)
      - Publications, 1946/1956 (Box 2)
      - Publications of the Institute for Social Research, 1955 (Box 2)
      - Publications of the Institute for Social Research, September, 1952 Through November, 1953, undated (Box 2)
      - Selected Books, undated (Box 2)
      - Supplementary Publication List
        - September 1956-December 1957, 1958 (Box 2)
        - September 1956-January 1960 (Box 2)
        - January 1960-May 1961 (Box 2)
        - 1962 [1963] (Box 2)
    - Brochures
      - Institute for Social Research Program Advertisements and Services, 1950-1987 (Box 2)
      - Monitoring the Future Program, 1975-2000 (Box 2)
      - Monographs published by the Institute for Social Research (arranged by title) A-Z, undated; 5 folders (Box 2)
      - Osiris IV, undated (Box 2)
      - The Search for Social Understanding: The Story of the Institute for Social Research at the University of Michigan... it's contribution to society... and its need for new quarters, undated (Box 2)
      - Survey Research Techniques, 1962; 1984 (Box 2)
    - Flyers
      - ISR Bookshelf, undated (Box 2)
      - University of Michigan Announces Institute for Social Research, circa 1946 (Box 2)
    - Histories
      - Institute for Social Research, 1950 (Box 2)
      - Institute for Social Research, 1946-1956, circa 1956 (Box 2)
      - Institute for Social Research, 1946-1961, undated (Box 2)
      - Two Papers Describing the Origins, History, and Present Organizational Life of the Institute, 1965 (Box 2)
      - Two Papers Describing the Origins, History, and Present Organizational Life of the Institute, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Lectures
      - Papers Presented by Staff Members of the Institute for Social Research at the Meeting of the American Psychological Association at Denver, Colorado, September 1949 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      - Driving Development Newsletter, 1970 (Box 2)
      - FYI, 1975-1987; 12 folders (Box 2)
      - FYI, 1988-1991; 1994; 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Freestyle, 1978-1980; 3 folders (Box 3)
      - ISR Newsletter
        - 1961-1962 (Box 3)
        - 1966-1968 (Box 3)
        - , vol. 1-5, 1969-1977; 1 volumes (Box 3)
        - , vol. 1, no. 3-4, 1969 (Box 3)
        - , vol. 1, no. 9 and 11, 1971 (Box 3)
        - , vol. 4, no. 3, 1976 (Box 3)
        - , vol. 6-17, 1978-1992; 1 volumes (Box 3)
          [title changes to Profiles: The ISR Newsletter]
        - , vol. 13, no. 3, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
        - , vol. 14, no. 2, 1986 (Box 3)
        - , vol. 15, no. 1, 1987 (Box 3)
        - , vol. 17, no. 3, 1992 (Box 3)
      - ISR Sampler, 2000-2002 (Box 3)
      - ISR Update, 2002 (Box 3)
      - Open Channel, 1969-1973; 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Profiles: The ISR Newsletter,, vol. 18-19, 1994-1995; 2 folders (Box 3)
        [Supersedes ISR Newsletter)
    - Proposals
      - Informed Leadership and Active Citizenship: A Program of Research and Action in National Affairs, 1951 (Box 3)
    - Reports
      - Changing Federal Strategies for Supporting Educational Research, Development, and Statistics, 1998 (Box 3)
      - Computers and the Schools: The Next Decade, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Computers in Higher Education: Computer-Based Tutorials in Introductory Biology, 1987 (Box 3)
      - Electronic Learning from Audiotape to Videodisc, 1986 (Box 3)
      - A Longitudinal Study of Family Economics: A Brief Description of an Ongoing Panel Study, 1969 (Box 3)
      - The Implementation of VCM (Value Centered Management) at the Institute for Social Research, 1995 (Box 3)
      - Overseeing the Nation's Report Card: The Creation and Evolution of the National Assessment Governing Board (NAGB), 1998 (Box 3)
      - Perceptions of Safety and Security at the University of Michigan: A Report to the Task Force on Campus Security and Safety, undated (Box 3)
      - Perceptions of Safety and Security at the University of Michigan: A Report to the Task Force on Campus Security and Safety, Part 1: Summary of Findings, Technical Report and Questionnaire, 1989 (Box 3)
      - Perceptions of Safety and Security at the University of Michigan: A Report to the Task Force on Campus Security and Safety, Part 2: Codebook and Breakdown of Responses by Occupation, Sex and Race of Respondent, 1989 (Box 3)
      - Perceptions of the Work environment for Non-Instructional Staff at the University of Michigan, 1995 (Box 3)
      - Progress Report on the Evaluation of the Michigan Campus Compact, 1991 (Box 3)
      - The Prudential Experiment, Preliminary Results, 1952 (Box 3)
      - Statistical Research Laboratory, final Report on Needs Assessment Survey, 1988 (Box 3)
      - Surveys of Consumer Attitudes: Tables and Charts, 1980 (Box 3)
      - Taking the Measure of Channel One, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Sub-Unit Publications
    The Sub-Unit Publications subseries includes annual reports, bibliographies, brochures, bulletins, manuals, newsletters, and reports from the Business Office, Center for Political Studies, Center for Research on Utilization of Scientific Knowledge (CRUSK), Computers in Early Literacy (CIEL Project), Program for Research on Black Americans, Research Center for Group Dynamics, and the Survey Research Center. For the papers of the Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research (ICPSR), the researcher should consult the separate finding aid.
    - Business Office (Box 4)
      The Business Office publications are annual financial reports scattered from 1977 through 1992. The Center for Political Studies includes brochures on the research program on race and American politics. Center for Research on Utilization of Scientific Knowledge (CRUSK) includes bibliographies and brochures announcing publications produced by the center. There are three issues of the CRUSK Newsletter from 1967. Also included under CRUSK is a report by the Energy Policy Group. The newsletter Scribbles will be found under Computers in Early Literacy (CIEL Project).
      - Annual Reports
        - ISR Operations for Fiscal Year..., 1977-1980 (Box 4)
        - Annual Report of Financial Operations, 1980-1981; 1981 (Box 4)
        - Annual Report of Financial Operations..., 1984; 1986 (Box 4)
        - Annual report of Financial Operations, 1987-1988 (Box 4)
        - Annual Report of Financial Operations Fiscal Year 1991-92, 1992 (Box 4)
        - Year Ending Comparative Statements, 1995-1996 (Box 4)
    - Center for Political Studies (CPS)
      - Research Program on Race and American Politics
        - Brochures, undated (Box 4)
    - Center for Research on Utilization of Scientific Knowledge (CRUSK)
      - Bibliographies
        - Publications, undated (Box 4)
      - Brochures
        - Announcements for Books Published by CRUSK, undated (Box 4)
        - CRUSK Reports on Knowledge Utilization and Social Research, 1975-1977 (Box 4)
        - CRUSK Short Reports, undated (Box 4)
      - Flyers, undated (Box 4)
      - Newsletters
        - CRUSK Newsletter, 1967 (Box 4)
      - Statistics
        - Staff Members Survey Report of Results, 1977 (Box 4)
      - Energy Policy Group
        - Reports
          - The Use of Conservation and Solar Energy in Michigan, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Computers in Early Literacy (CIEL Project)
      - Newsletters
        - Scribbles, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Program for Research on Black Americans
      The Program for Research on Black Americans includes a bibliography entitled Research and Training Activities of the Program for Research on Black Americans. Volume 1 of the newsletter Program for Research on Black Americans was published in 1967. There is also a series of occasional papers entitled Perspectives, beginning in 1995.
      - Bibliographies
        - Research and Training Activities of the Program for Research on Black Americans
          - 1988 (Box 4)
          - 1990 (Box 4)
          - 1992 (Box 4)
      - Newsletters
        - Program for Research on Black Americans, vol. 1, 1991 (Box 4)
      - Reports
        - Perspectives: An Occasional Report Spring 1995, Fall 1999, Fall and Winter 2000 (Box 4)
    - Research Center for Group Dynamics (RCGD)
      The Research Center for Group Dynamics published a bibliography entitled Bibliography of Research in Children, Youth and Family Life at the Institute for Social Research. They also produced at report on the center in 1950 and 1994.
      - Bibliographies
        - Bibliography of Research in Children, Youth and Family Life at the Institute for Social Research, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Brochures
        - Books Published by the Research Center for Group Dynamics, undated (Box 4)
      - Flyers, undated (Box 4)
      - Reports
        - The Research Center for Group Dynamics, 1950 (Box 4)
        - RCGD Faculty Research and Teaching Interests, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Survey Research Center (SRC)
      The Survey Research Center (SRC) (2.5 linear feet) has published annual reports, brochures, flyers, numerous newsletters, reports, and surveys. The annual reports cover the early years of the SRC from 1948-1950. There is also one annual report covering the period 1984-1985. The Survey Research Center produced the newsletter Economic Outlook USA from 1974 through 1990. The Bentley Library holds volumes 1-14, 1974-1988.
      SRC reports are arranged alphabetically by title. There are several themes covered in these reports. Early reports from 1948-1951 deal with United States citizens' perceptions of the Soviet Union, foreign policy, atomic energy, atomic warfare, and civil defense. The Survey Research Center also studied labor relations, morale, and productivity of Chesapeake and Ohio railway workers and Prudential Insurance Company of America clericals during the late 1940s and early 1950s. In 1968 they reported on an inter-company labor study entitled Improving a Company's Total Performance Through Time: An Inter-Company Longitudinal Study and the Development of Human Resource Accounting. The Survey Research Center also published Industrial Location Decisions in the Detroit Area in 1972.
      The Survey Research Center has spent much time analyzing the university and higher education with reports such as Study of Higher Education in Michigan in 1959; Faculty Appraisal of the University Library in 1961; and Highlights from a Study of Attitudes and Opinions of Non-Academic Employees at the University of Michigan published in 1965. In 1988 the SRC published the report Perceptions of the University of Michigan Within the University Community and Among Residents of Michigan. This report surveyed Michigan residents and University faculty and students and compared their reactions to the University of Michigan with Wayne State University, Michigan State University and Central Michigan University.
      In 1985 the Survey Research Center studied the effects of the capital gains exclusion on senior citizens in the report Federal Policy and the Mobility of Older Homeowners: The Effects of the One-Time Capital Gains Exclusion. The SRC also prepared a series of reports entitled Rental Housing in Ann Arbor: Summary of Preliminary Findings Prepared for the Department of Housing and Urban Development Under Contract With the City of Ann Arbor in 1976. In 1965 the Survey Research Center produced a report entitled Housing at the University of Michigan: Report of a Survey of American Students.
      There are also bulletins and posters from 1948 through 2001 that describe the Survey Research Techniques training program, held at the Annual Summer Institute of the Survey Research Center.
      - Annual Reports
        - Progress Report of the Survey Research Center, 1948 (Box 4)
        - Second Annual Report of the Survey Research Center, 1949 (Box 4)
        - Year End Letter, 1949 (Box 4)
        - Annual Report, 1950 (Box 4)
        - A Brief Statement of the Activities of the Survey Research Center, 1946-1950; 1950 (Box 4)
        - Annual Report of Survey Research Center, 1985 (Box 4)
        - Survey Research Center, 1985-1986 (Box 4)
        - Annual Report, 1998-2000 (Box 4)
      - Brochures
        - General, undated (Box 4)
        - Centro de Investigaciones Sociales por Muestreo, undated (Box 4)
        - Computer Techniques in Social Science Research, undated (Box 4)
        - Economic Outlook USA, undated (Box 4)
        - Human Relations, 1947 (Box 4)
        - Monitoring Economic Change, undated (Box 4)
        - Services and Facilities, 1982 (Box 4)
        - Survey Booklets, 1983-1984; undated (Box 4)
      - Flyers, undated (Box 4)
      - Manuals
        - Manual for Interviewers of the Survey Research Center, 1955; undated (Box 4)
      - Newsletters
        - Center Survey, 1991-2002; 12 folders (Box 4)
        - Center Survey, 2003-2005; 3 folders (Box 5)
        - Economic Outlook USA, vol. 1-14, 1974-1988; 14 folders (Box 5)
        - La Red/The Net, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
        - News From the Center, vol. 1, 1982 (Box 5)
        - Staff Letter, 1954 (Box 5)
      - Press Releases, 1975-1996 (Box 5)
      - Reports
        - An Analysis of Soviet Society, Third Progress Report, 1948 (Box 5)
        - An Analysis of Soviet Society, Part I: The Interview Data, 1949 (Box 5)
        - An Analysis of Soviet Society, Part II: Three Illustrative Interviews, 1949 (Box 5)
        - Attitudes Toward United States--Russian Relations: A National Survey, 1948 (Box 5)
        - Defense of Our Cities: A Study of Public Attitudes on Civil Defense, 1951 (Box 5)
        - Detroit Edison Study: Work Morale of Non-Supervisory Employees as Related to Their Evaluation of the Consultative Skills of Their Supervision, Special Report No. 5, 1949 (Box 5)
        - Development of Questionnaire Measures of Employee Reactions to Their Jobs, 1962 (Box 5)
        - Factors Related to Differences in Group Productivity: A Study of Maintenance of Way Section Gangs on the Pere Marquette District of the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway, 1949 (Box 5)
        - Faculty Appraisal of the University Library, 1961 (Box 5)
        - Five Selected Interviews from a Study of Public Thinking Regarding Atomic Energy, [ca. 1950] (Box 5)
        - Highlights from a Study of Attitudes and Opinions of Non-Academic Employees at the University of Michigan, 1965 (Box 5)
        - Housing at the University of Michigan: Report of a Survey of American Students, 1965 (Box 5)
        - Human Relations Program
          - A Comparative Study of Worker, Steward and Foreman Attitudes in a Unionized Automobile Factory, 1950 (Box 5)
          - An Experimental Study of Legislative Control in a Hierarchical Organization, 1953 (Box 5)
          - Human Relations Program of the Survey Research Center, 1950 (Box 5)
          - Research Proposal: A Study of the Effect of Management Changes on the Productivity and Motivation of Civilian and Military Personnel in the Air Materiel Command, 1952 (Box 5)
        - Human Relations Series
          - Productivity, Supervision and Employee Morale...Selected Findings From a Study of Clerical Workers in the Prudential Insurance Company of America, Study No. 6, 1948 (Box 6)
          - Productivity, Supervision and Morale in an Office Situation, Series 2, Report 1, 1950 (Box 6)
          - A Program of Research on the Fundamental Problems of Organizing Human Behavior, 1947 (Box 6)
        - Human Relations Study Techniques, 1949 (Box 6)
        - Improving a Company's Total Performance Through Time: An Inter-Company Longitudinal Study and the Development of Human Resource Accounting, includes Proposal, 1968 (Box 6)
        - Industrial Location Decisions in the Detroit Area, 1972 (Box 6)
        - 1980 SRC National Sample: Design and Development, 1986 (Box 6)
        - Percentage of All Items, Non-Supervisory Interview, Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Study, Study no. 31, 1950 (Box 6)
        - Percentage Distribution of All Items, Foreman Interview Schedule, Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Study, Study no. 31, 1950 (Box 6)
        - Perceptions of the University of Michigan Within the University Community and Among Residents of Michigan, 1988 (Box 6)
        - A Proposed Program of Research on the Fundamental Problems of Organizing Human Behavior, undated (Box 6)
        - Public Attitudes Toward American Foreign Policy: Attitudes Toward the Major Issues of Foreign Policy, 1947 (Box 6)
        - Public Reaction to the Atomic Bomb and World Affairs: A Nation-wide Survey of Attitudes and Information, 1947 (Box 6)
        - Public Response to Peacetime Uses of Atomic Energy, v .II Individual and Group Analysis, 1951 (Box 6)